But the goal of my journey is this.
不过我旅行的目的是这个
To meet my friend who embarked on a journey ten years ago.
找到十年前踏上旅途的朋友
Did you find out where Gorilla went?
知道大猩猩的去向了吗？
Tür.
提尤亚
It's a trade city in the northern lands.
那是北方诸国的贸易都市
It's farther east from here.
要从这里往东边走吧
In the opposite direction from Äußerst.
跟奥伊萨斯特是反方向呢
Yeah.
是啊
Frieren,
芙莉莲
I embarked on this journey in order to find Gorilla.
我是为了找到大猩猩 才踏上这趟旅途的
I know.
我知道喔
Either way, the sun is about to set,
总之 太阳也快下山了
so can't we hold off on deciding until tomorrow?
要不要等到明天再做决定？
I was able to rent a cabin.
村民说可以借我们小木屋
They said we're free to use it.
他们说我们可以自由使用喔
Thank you.
谢谢
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田钟人 作画：阿部司）
I brought some firewood.
我带了些柴火回来了
I bought groceries so we can make dinner.
我买了可以做晚饭的食材
My hands are so cold.
我的手好冰
It's starting to get pretty cold nowadays.
毕竟最近天气已经很冷了
You weren't joking. Wow…
真的耶 好冰喔
This is record-breaking.
这已经可以打破纪录了
Let me see…
我看看…
-You're right. It's so cold. -Isn't it?
-真的耶 好冰喔 -对吧？
Stop that!
不要啊！
-Isn't it record-breaking? -Yeah.
-破纪录了吧？ -对
-So cold… -Jeez…
-好冰 -真是的
It's snowing.
下雪了
Will we have to wait out the winter again?
会不会又要等这个冬季过去才能走？
This time, it's not like we have to pass a steep mountain range.
这次我们又不是要翻山越岭
It'll be fine unless it turns into a blizzard or something.
只要不演变成暴风雪一类的 就没问题了
It did.
变成暴风雪了
-It sure did. -It did.
-真的呢 -确实
Cold spells in this region last for at least a month.
这一带的寒流 至少会持续一个月的时间
You shouldn't travel too far.
最好不要去太远的地方
You can use that cabin for the time being.
这段时间你们都可以使用这间小屋
What do you want to do, Sein? Do you want to depart?
怎么办 赞因？你要就此出发吗？
Do you even need to ask?
这还需要问吗？
I guess we're stuck until the cold spell passes.
看来只能在这里等寒流过去了
Yup.
就是啊
Well, there's a bar and a general store, and the cabin is spacious.
不过 这里反正有酒吧跟杂货店 小木屋也很大
It's much better compared to the mountain cabin from last time.
跟上次的山间小屋比起来好太多了
And most importantly, this village has
更重要的是 这个村里
a magic store run by a suspicious old person.
有一个可疑老人经营的魔法商店
Based on my experience,
根据我的经验
you can find legendary spells in places like that.
这种地方都能找到传说级的魔法
Being able to explore that store is a big plus.
能够好好逛逛那家店真是大加分
Legendary spells?
传说级的魔法？
What kinds have you found in the past?
你至今为止都找到了哪些魔法啊？
Spells to get rid of mold
消灭霉菌的魔法
and spells to remove tough oil stains.
还有清除顽固油渍的魔法
Wow.
好厉害
That's true. Those useful spells were life-changing.
这么好用的魔法 确实已经能够改变世界了
They sound like tips you learn from your grandma.
好像奶奶会教的日常生活小贴士
Either way, all we can do now is wait.
总之现在只能等暴风雪结束了
You'll die if you take winter in the northern lands lightly.
小看北方诸国的冬天可是会送命的
After all, Master Stark almost died in the Schwer Mountains.
上次在休维亚山脉 休塔尔克大人差点就死掉了
I was raised in the northern lands.
我也在北方诸国长大
I know that much.
这点我当然清楚
Well, I guess we'll be together for a little while longer.
看来我们还会再相处一段时间呢
The cold spell should end soon.
寒流差不多快结束了
You adventurers can finally depart.
各位冒险者终于能出发了呢
Yeah, that's right.
是啊 说得没错
Hey, we barely spent time together.
咦？我们几乎没有怎么待在一起呢
-Sein. -Huh?
-赞因 -怎么了？
-Do you have a moment? -What's wrong, Frieren?
-有空吗？ -怎么了 芙莉莲？
It's rare to see you at the bar.
在酒吧看到你还真是稀奇啊
Stark and Fern are acting strange.
休塔尔克跟菲伦之间不太对劲
I think they're fighting. Be their mediator.
八成是吵架了 你去调解吧
I don't mind doing that, but why are you asking me?
我是没问题啦 但为什么你要找我去？
Mediating is a priest's job.
调解是僧侣的工作啊
It is?
有这种事？
This looks bad.
情况看起来很糟呢
Hey, what happened?
喂 究竟发生什么事了？
It's Master Stark's fault.
都是休塔尔克大人的错
Yes, it is all my fault.
是 全都是我不好
This is going nowhere.
这样不是办法
Come to the room next door, one at a time.
轮流到隔壁的房间来
So, what happened?
说吧 到底怎么了？
When we first moved into this cabin,
刚住进这间小屋时
Fern touched my cheek with her cold hands, remember?
菲伦不是曾经 用她冷冰冰的手摸我的脸颊吗？
Yeah.
是有这件事
Today, I did the same thing to her…
今天我也对她做了同样的举动
-And Fern just blew up. -How childish.
-然后菲伦就火大了 -你们是小孩子吗？
Did you really think a girl would like to have your hands all over her face?
有哪个女孩子会喜欢突然被摸脸啊？
-Do you want things to stay like this? -I want to make peace.
-你要继续这样下去吗？ -我想跟她和好
Stark, unlike me, you are a genuinely good guy.
休塔尔克 你跟我不同 你天生就是个好人
So just say your honest feelings.
所以只要诚实说出你的感受即可
If you want to make peace, let that person know.
你想跟她和好的话 就说出来让她知道
Frieren's not going to mediate between you two.
芙莉莲可不会帮你们俩调解喔
Yeah, I know. I'll apologize to Fern.
嗯 我知道了 我会跟菲伦道歉
Stark regrets what he did.
休塔尔克已经在反省了
He's just a kid. He didn't mean any harm.
他只是个小鬼 他那样对你并没有恶意
I know.
我知道
I was just stubborn.
是我刚刚太固执了
I want to apologize.
我想跟他道歉
I'm the one who started it, anyway.
而且这件事本来就是因我而起
The fact that he touched me wasn't the issue.
被他摸到脸其实没有关系
It's just that…
只是…
he held my shoulder down with such strong force.
他按住我肩膀的时候 力气好大
It made me feel scared, just a little.
所以我就有点被吓到了
Do you hate Stark?
你讨厌休塔尔克吗？
Why would you ask such a thing? Does it come across that way?
你为什么这么问呢？ 看起来像这样吗？
Then let him know that you felt scared and make peace with him.
那就让他知道你其实是感到害怕 然后跟他和好吧
-Be more gentle with me. -I'm sorry.
-请你对我更温柔点 -对不起
Just get together already!
给我赶快交往啊！
I don't know what you're talking about, but I can tell you're doing your best.
虽然不清楚你在说什么 但我看得出来你很努力了
Thank you. That was really helpful.
谢谢你 真是帮了我大忙了
Frieren, you are the only one.
芙莉莲 就只有你
-You commend me as if I'm a kid. -You are a kid.
-把我当小孩称赞 -你就是个小孩啊
It doesn't feel too bad, I guess.
不过 这种感觉还不错
Hey, I've been wanting to ask…
对了 我一直都想问一件事
I've been thinking ever since you recruited me,
从你招我入队开始 我就在想
but why do you spend so much time and energy on me?
你为什么要对我这么执着呢？
Because I have an aversion to my own kind.
是因为出于对同类的厌恶吧
Seeing you refuse to go on an adventure
看着你拒绝踏上冒险的旅途
reminded me of myself before I departed to defeat the Demon King.
就让我想起出发去打倒魔王前的自己
And it annoyed me.
让我感到很生气
That doesn't explain why you would care about me.
光是这样并不能解释 你为什么对我那么执着
That's exactly why.
这就是理由啊
I think I just wanted to give you an opportunity.
我想我只是想给你一个契机吧
What does that mean?
你在说什么啊？
It's what Himmel the Hero would've done, that's all.
如果是勇者辛美尔 他一定会这么做
Take my hand, Frieren.
抓住我的手 芙莉莲
I will give you the opportunity to embark on a journey.
我会给你踏上旅途的契机
Himmel and everyone gave me the courage to step out
辛美尔他们给了我 跨出去那一步的勇气
and taught me the joy that comes from being with friends.
并且教会我跟伙伴同行的快乐
How was it, Sein? Wasn't it fun?
怎么样 赞因？很开心吧？
It was a lot of fun.
的确非常开心呢
We'll become heroes that nobody can forget, like Himmel the Hero.
我们要成为像勇者辛美尔那样 让人永远铭记于心的英雄
I'm talking about what you can do "now," Sein.
我在说的是“现在”啊 赞因
So I decided to believe in her words.
所以我决定相信她说的话
Gorilla always talked about you.
大猩猩总是提到你
He said that the two of you will become heroes whose names
他说你们会一起成为
will be engraved in history forever.
把名字永远刻在历史上的英雄
I'll follow after Gorilla, after all.
我还是要去追大猩猩
I don't want to have any more regrets.
我不想再有更多遗憾了
I understand.
我懂你的心情
Well, take care.
那你们多保重
See you.
以后见
You parted ways so easily.
还真是干净利落的分别啊
Unlike you two, Sein is an adult.
赞因跟你们不一样 他已经是个大人了
He'll be fine.
他一定没问题的
It's so quiet when you're alone…
一个人竟然会这么安静啊
29 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者辛美尔逝世的29年后）
OFFEN MOUNTAIN RANGE IN THE NORTHERN LANDS
（北方诸国 奥芬群山）
Oh? That's rare… She's still sleeping?
奇怪了 还真是罕见 她还在睡？
She's probably tired, since we've been walking nonstop.
毕竟最近 马不停蹄地赶路 应该累坏了吧
Good enough.
可以了
Hey, breakfast is ready.
喂 早餐已经做好咯
It's time to wake up.
差不多该起床了
Fern?
菲伦？
Hey, wake up, Frieren.
芙莉莲 快起来
Give me half a day…
再让我睡半天…
You can't sleep that much.
睡那么多不好吧
More importantly, Fern looks unwell.
更何况菲伦看起来不太舒服
Hey.
喂
Stop that.
别这样嘛
You have a fever.
你发烧了
Stay warm and sleep.
好好保暖 睡吧
Let's see…
我看看喔…
-What? That's weird… -I brought water.
-咦？奇怪… -我拿水来了
-Found it. -What's that?
-找到了 -那是什么？
A notebook about medicinal herbs that Sein left for us.
记载了药草的笔记 是赞因临行前留给我们的
Sein did that?
赞因吗？
If I diagnose the illness with magic,
只要用魔法诊断病症
I can find the right herbs to use.
我就能知道要用什么药草了
But you need the Magic of the Goddess to diagnose illnesses.
要诊断病症 不就得用女神大人的魔法吗？
I thought only people with Scriptures could use that.
我以为只有 持有《圣典》的人才能用那种魔法
I have Scriptures too.
我也有《圣典》喔
It's being used as a placemat!
你竟然拿《圣典》垫锅子！
I may not be gifted like a priest,
我或许没有僧侣的天赋
but I can at least do a simple diagnosis.
但简单的病症诊断还是可以做的
-I don't know about complicated illnesses. -Can we trust you?
-但是复杂的病症我就不行了 -你真的没问题吗？
Yeah, it's just a common cold.
嗯 只是普通的感冒而已
Medicinal herbs that grow in this area are…
生长在这一带的药草是…
That reminds me…
说起来
I collected medicinal herbs around here with Himmel and everyone.
以前跟辛美尔他们 在这附近采过药草呢
For now, let's move to where we can stay warm.
总之 我们先找个温暖的地方吧
You're right.
说得也对
Oh my.
哎呀
What a lifesaver.
真是帮了大忙了
Who would've thought that someone lived in these mountains.
没想到居然有人住在这种深山里
The last time I came, there was a village.
上次我来的时候 这里还有村庄
That was decades ago.
那是几十年前的事情了
It was a prestigious village that even the hero visited once.
当年村子可是出名到 连勇者大人都来过呢
Well anyway, get some rest here.
总之 你们应该要好好休息
Thank you.
谢谢你
By the way, wasn't there an icicle cherry blossom tree around here?
话说回来 这附近是不是有一棵冰柱樱？
Yes, north of here.
对 从这里往北走
It's a bit complicated to get to.
只是要找到那棵树不容易喔
It's fine.
没关系
I've been here before.
我之前来过这里
All right then, I'll be working.
那好吧 我要去工作了
Wait here, Fern.
在这里等我们 菲伦
We'll go get ingredients for your medicine.
我们去采制药的药材给你
You've been holding her hand ever since we got here.
从我们到这里之后 你就一直握着她的手不放
She looks like she's in pain.
因为她看起来很难受啊
When Fern catches a cold, holding her hand comforts her.
菲伦感冒的时候 握住她的手就能让她感到安心
She's been like this ever since she was small.
她从小时候就是这样了
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Mistress Frieren,
芙莉莲大人
you're embarrassing me.
这样我很难为情啊
Why?
为什么？
Please don't treat me like a child.
请不要再把我当成小孩来看待了
I see. You're right.
这样啊 你说得没错
She'll be a full-fledged adult in just two years, huh?
再过两年 菲伦就是独当一面的大人了
Just the other day, she was a little girl about this tall.
明明不久前还是个 个头只有这样高的小孩子
I was much taller than her too.
我都还比她高呢
Time flew by.
真是岁月不饶人
In my mind, Fern is still just a child.
在我眼中 菲伦依旧是个孩子
That probably won't change from now on.
这点大概以后也不会改变吧
Frieren…
芙莉莲…
We'd better hurry up and gather the ingredients.
还是赶快去收集药材吧
Yeah.
好
The icicle cherry blossom tree is around here.
冰柱樱应该就在这附近了
That icicle cherry blossom
那个冰柱樱
is the last ingredient, huh?
就是最后一个药材吧？
We actually need the mushroom that grows on the tree's roots.
其实我们需要的 是长在树根附近的蘑菇
It's beautiful.
好美啊
I wish Fern could've seen it too.
真希望菲伦也能亲眼看到
This is probably my favorite flower that blooms in the winter.
在冬季绽放的花里 这大概是我最喜欢的花了
The flowers are poisonous, so be careful.
这种花有毒 要小心点
Hey,
话说
why did you hold Fern's hand?
你刚刚干嘛握着菲伦的手？
You normally don't treat her like a child.
平常你也不会拿她当孩子看待啊
I didn't mean to treat her like a child.
我那么做并不是把她当孩子看
I only held her hand because she looked like she was in pain.
只是因为菲伦她看起来很难受才握的
That's the only method I know to relieve pain.
能舒缓他人痛苦的办法 我就只知道这一个
I wonder what I was supposed to do instead?
我到底该怎么做才好呢？
If that's the case, just do what you feel is best.
如果是这样的话 那就做你真心想做的事吧
At least, that's what my master did.
至少我师父是这么做的
I believe people need emotional support.
应该是因为人总是需要情感上的支持
And no one would complain about getting support.
而且没有人会因为被关心而有怨言吧
What is this about?
这是做什么？
You were having a nightmare.
你刚刚做噩梦了
People feel vulnerable when they're sick.
人生病的时候总会感到很脆弱
My mother, who died when I was small,
我小时候就过世的母亲
used to hold my hand like this.
在这种时候都会握住我的手
It's comforting.
这种感觉让人很安心
That's because you were a child.
那是因为你当时是个小孩子吧
It's not only children who need emotional support.
需要情感支持的并不只有小孩子而已
It doesn't feel so bad, right?
这样感觉还不赖吧？
I guess so.
说得是呢
It's not too bad.
感觉还不错
I'm so thoughtful and handsome, aren't I?
懂得体贴别人的我很帅气吧？
Shut up.
闭嘴啦
Your medicine is ready.
药已经做好了
Fern was probably embarrassed because I was there.
菲伦会感到难为情 大概是因为我在场的缘故
Nobody would want others to see themselves getting spoiled.
毕竟没有人喜欢 被看到自己撒娇的样子吧
Thank you, Stark.
谢谢你 休塔尔克
I'll do what I feel is best.
我会按照我的真心行动的
In return, when you catch a cold, I will hold your hand.
作为回报 你感冒的时候 我也会握住你的手
No way, that's embarrassing.
才不要 那也太难为情了吧
All right, let's get this mushroom.
好 赶快采蘑菇吧
Up we go.
嘿咻
I didn't expect it to be that big! How scary!
这蘑菇也太大了吧！好恐怖啊！
Now, just add the other ingredients
接下来只要加进其他药材
and mix it very, very well.
好好搅拌均匀…
She looks like a witch. So scary!
看起来好像魔女啊 超级恐怖啊！
Open your mouth, Fern.
把嘴巴张开 菲伦
You're so good at this. What a great help.
你还真能干 帮了我一个大忙
You think so?
是这样吗？
Don't worry, you'll get better soon.
放心吧 你很快就会好起来了
Mistress Frieren, I'm not a child anymore…
芙莉莲大人 我不是小孩子了…
I know.
我知道
Take care now!
你们之后要多保重喔！
Thank you very much.
真的非常感谢您
You seem much better.
你看起来好很多了
It's thanks to Mistress Frieren,
这都是托了 芙莉莲大人、休塔尔克大人
Master Stark, and Master Sein.
还有赞因大人的福
And I really owe that person
还有那位把房子借我们的老太太
who lent us their house.
我欠了她好大的人情
All right.
好
Well then,
那么
let's head to Äußerst, the city of magic.
朝魔法之都奥伊萨斯特出发吧
-Can you show me that? -Come at me.
-那个能借我看看吗？ -放马过来
-This year is full of potential. -You wanna fight?
-今年真是卧虎藏龙 -要打一场吗？
-I can't do it alone. -You have them.
-我一个人办不到 -你的眼神
-The eyes of a killer. -No idea.
-充满杀意 -不知道
"First-Class Mage Exam."
《一级魔法使选拔测验》
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译：洪贞韵